So Matt, today we're going to be talking
uh about agents to wrap up the uh wrap
up the conference and a really
interesting topic, agent experience. Um
what is agent what is agent experience
to you? Well, I mean that's that's what
I'm gonna be talking a lot about, right?
like but agent experience or AX is is
really
um I I coined that term during a a talk
with one of our principal engineers just
because we were talking about like we we
were starting to build more and more
around coding agents integrating in with
Netlifi and and and building and
deploying on Netlifi right like and we
were seeing you know looking into some
of the flows and seeing some of the
things that worked and didn't work so
well right like and suddenly just like
on that call said the words like yeah we
got to as we start building our features
we really got to start thinking about
the agent experience of them and then it
sort of dawned on me that like that's
actually like a pretty broad concern
like this this idea of of of of AX or
agent experience what what does it mean
to build products that are not just used
by other human beings but that are also
used by agents and through agents
awesome Well, Matt, I'm I'm intrigued to
to learn more. So, I'll bring your
slides up on stage and I'll pass the mic
over to you. So, Matt, take it away.
Thank you, Simon. Um, great to great to
see you all. Hope you've had an an
amazing conference so far. Thanks for
for having me here. I'm the CEO and
co-founder of Netifi. We're a web
deployment platform. um been around for
for about 10 years now with the vision
of of of helping to build a a a better
web and um enable the world's developers
to create and and and unlock the power
of the web.
And before I get to agent experience, I
want to just think back to like when
when when I started building uh
applications and and and building
software. Um back then Don Norman and
and and a fellow countryman from Denmark
Jacob Nelson coin co coined the term
user experience or UX um with the
definition of being all aspect of the
end users interaction with the company
its services and its product and
obviously um user experience turned out
to be incredibly important to building
software right like we started realizing
that software is is not just a list of
features. It's also something you
interact with built by a comic company
often with a community around it. One of
the my my favorite articles about it
back in the day was u this one about why
you only need to test with with with
five users. And just this realization
that if you if you really get down to
the human level and you're building a
new product and you get like five people
to just sit down and use it without
telling them how they should use it, you
often you often get this kind of
experience where it turns out to be
surprisingly difficult to to to approach
your your software. um you think
everything is logical and obvious, but
that's rarely the case for for for a
completely new user coming to
it. And it turned out back in the day
that that that UX could be a massive
differentiator from one product to to to
the competing products, right? Um
originally maybe we thought
about products as as mainly just like
can they do a job or not? Do they have
the features? And it turned out that how
they do that job and how it feels like
to to use them, how low the friction
gets as a user adopting a new product
was really crucial in in in winning the
market. Then when when when I started
Netlifi and and we launched 10 years
ago, we we had this mission of unlocking
the power of the web for for in many
ways for a new group of developers. At
the time, a front-end developer was
often seen as someone that would take a
Photoshop file and hand like slice it up
and then hand it over to a real
developer that would implement it in in
in a back end. And we had this vision of
a different kind of web architecture
where we would build everything with
with native web technologies and where
the front-end developer would be the
main developer. And my thesis back then
was that developer experience, this
holistic um interface with our company,
with our product, with our community
would be what would differentiate a
platform like ours from our competitors.
in that we had to build the best
holistic experience around pushing your
ideas to the web to to really get this
new way of building for the web to take
off. Um to help front-end developers
just become web developers and to
differentiate in the in in the market
and again to really live up to both
these pieces of of of the foundation of
our company, right? like enabling the
world's developers to create and unlock
the power of the web and and and to
actually build a better
web. And developer experience is really
defined again as the holistic experience
a developer have when building on on a
platform. It's it's not just the
technology or the list of features. It's
the onboarding. How intuitive and
frictionless it is it? It's the
documentation plays a big role in
understanding a software platform for
for a developer. The brand is relevant.
The software libraries and SDKs and CLI
tooling that you make available to sort
of integrate with a developer native
environment. And if you want to build
great developer experience, again, it's
not like a set of features that that
makes a great DX. It's really an
obsession over the developer as a core
persona that you that you constantly
think about as you're building your
product. And then um at the at at the
start of of 2023 as AI started to sort
of really be a massive market trend and
we defined our AI strategy. One one
piece that that I started talking about
internally was like what do we need to
do to become the preferred deployment
platform for for AI. And I got to be
honest and say that in the start of 23
when I said that it it felt like okay
this is this is a very long-term thing.
This is probably more something that's
going to be relevant by the end of the
by the end of the decade than than right
around the corner. And boy was I wrong.
Right. like it it the the the ability
for agents to write code has accelerated
incredibly fast and this became really
relevant really fast. So at the start of
this year, I published an an article
called introducing AX, why agent
experience matters. that really was part
of of of reentering
Netlifi on the idea of of agent
experience on the idea that that that we
now have in many ways new class of of
users that are agents building and
deploying on top of our product or um
users building and deploying on Netlifi
through agents and just just like with
user experience, if you start actually
like really taking your product and you
just give them their your your CLI tool
and and some APIs and and you start um
asking it to use it, often often you get
a similar effect just with an an agent
instead of a a user hallucinating
non-existing features trying to go for
API calls that doesn't necessarily do
what they what they think. Um and it and
it quickly became visible to me that
like agent
experience is is a whole new discipline
an incredibly important discipline. So
what is agent experience? Again agent ax
is is the holistic experience an AI
agent will have as the user of a product
or or platform.
Um, I'll talk to a lot more of the
practical patterns that that we've been
using as we've been building out the
agent experience for for Netifi and how
we think about agent experience in in in
in general. Um, part of is is simply
making platforms or products available
to
agents. Now, every every web app is
somewhat available to to an agent,
right? like you can spin up operator
from from chat tbt or you can spin up um
compute use from claude and be able to
to to do stuff with a web app whether
the web app wants to or not. But it also
seems logical that like simulating human
users through a virtual browser and
screenshots fed into a multimodal agent
can't be the best experience for an
agent.
and agents will be collaborators at the
intersection of of of humans and and
products. So I started driving my team
towards obsessing over the agent as a
core persona as a core user of
Netlifi with the thesis that within the
next couple of years anyone that is not
building a great agent experience is not
going to be able to build a great
developer experience either. And with
the thesis that agent experience is
going to be a part of differentiating
products and platforms from their
competitors, which product is the
agents preferring, which product works
best with the agent of choice for any of
your users, that's going to be a key
part in building successful products in
the
future. When we think of of of AX from
the perspective of of Netlifi, we think
about Netlifi's own AX, how how are we
building Netifi to be easy for agents to
consume and build on and deploy on?
Um there's
a there's what we call customer AX.
That's the other side of it, right? Like
every single company that that uses
Netlifi as a platform to build products
on or build websites on or build
e-commerce on are probably also in the
future going to have to think about the
agent experience of the products they
build and and we're in this interesting
position to to to help them do that. And
then we are thinking of the broader
industry AX that I'll talk more about
where where where as a industry we kind
of all have to work together to start
building standards and conventions for
how agents interact with all of our
products. Let's start with with Netifi's
own AX and and and what we've done
there. In in some ways our journey
started already back in in in May 23
just about two years ago now when um
OpenAI launched the GPT store for Chat
GPT. Back then we built a custom GPT
called Netlifi's website deployer. Um,
and it used a a a flow that that we had
built early on in Netlifi, but that we
then really tailored specifically to
these agents where within the chat GPT
universe, as soon as you have discovered
this GPT, you can just add mention
Netlifi and say deploy this thing on a
URL and chat TPT will will will
instantly deploy and give you back a URL
without any friction. No sign up, no
authorization, nothing like that. just
just the agent doing a deploy on your
behalf and giving you a URL you can
share with the world and then it would
also give you a claim link. So if you
wanted to keep that URL around for more
than a couple of hours, you could go
follow that link, claim the site and and
and and add it to your Netlifi account.
And we sort of just gradually discovered
after a while that that that suddenly we
were we we were seeing about like we
were seeing more than thousand sites
created every every single day just from
the chatbt
ecosystem. And then we started expanding
this and writing guides and tutorials
for for agents to build on top of
Netlifi and use similar claims flow
whether they were deploying through
GitHub repositories or directly to
Netlifi. And at the end of last year, we
saw like the launches of um Bold and
actually Bold and Lovable launched kind
of at the same time and and and to me
really pushed the the barrier for what
agents could do to the to the next level
and suddenly like propelled us from from
a world where where it was very much
prototyping space or small FML apps to a
space where where it became obvious that
okay Now probably these agents are
starting to be the natural starting
point for for a new project. Even if you
just if you if you take the code they
initially set up and start working with
it somewhere else. It started being
clear that it was just like an
incredibly fast way to get a new product
going. And it also became really visible
that that agents would um start
working much better for coding websites
much faster than I had initially
thought. Bold is is fully integrated
with Netlifi as Simon mentioned. So if
you build a product and hit deploy that
deploy directly flows to Netifi. It uses
this claim flow where there's no
friction on the behalf of the user.
There's no use to there's no need to
first sign up and and
and then go back to Bold and ask it to
do things. Bolt can just start
deploying. Um
and about a month ago, um Windsurf
launched a similar partnership where if
you're working on a Windsurf project and
it's it's any kind of web project, you
can really just tell Windsurf deploy
this. It'll deploy it. You'll get a URL
on windsurf.build.
built. You can share it or use it or you
can go claim it if you want to keep it
around longer. Again, same completely
frictionless onboarding for an agent
doing work on behalf of a user. And
today we have many more partners like
same.dev dev or alpha refine and and and
several others that that are picking up
these workflows and using our platform
in a way where the agent is really in
the driver's seat to the point where
where today we're we're seeing about
10,000 sites created directly from
coding agents every single day on on on
Netlifi. It's pretty pretty wild to to
experience. And in my end, I've I've
centered my whole product team around AX
as the northstar of our product
experience. Just like developer
experience in the first 10 years of
Netifi was really the key part to
reducing the friction for a new
developer coming in and working on our
product.
I now have full conviction that if we
don't if we don't lead the space in the
agent experience in and in how simple
and how frictionless it is to use Netifi
with code agents will not be able to
deliver on a on on on the best developer
experience in in in the world. So what
does this mean in practice? Agent
experience um involves typically
involves levels of of authentication uh
onboarding flows and and maybe model
context
protocol systems, right? Like this is
the core question of like how can agents
actually interact with your system? Of
course, if if if your product doesn't
have an an an API, if it doesn't have
tooling for agents, if it doesn't have
an MCP, it's going to be very hard for
agents to actually interact with your
pro products. And most projects on a
platform like ours now starts with an
agent on behalf of a human. So, there's
always a human in the loop, but but it's
typically the agent instigating the
first deploy and the first motion.
Oaf is becoming an important standard
here also al also in MCP but I think
it's often still too much friction if
you constantly have to or off with a
bunch of tools before the agent can do
anything on your behalf so we we'll look
at more patterns around
that and with MCP it's also pretty
obvious that while MCP is sort of the
first whole the first winner at the
whole standard layer, the authorization
story there is still pretty rough and
and pretty
unclear. Docs and context files become
incredibly important. LLMs are are not
humans. They're like a very weird type
of developer that on the one hand has
has read everything on the
internet and and and on the other hand
they might be trying to use your product
without actually having looked at the
latest version of your docs. So there's
this weird intersection between knowing
very broad a lot of stuff and very deep
a lot of stuff but they might not
actually like be looking at your current
documentation. they might be trying to
build on your product using an an
outdated tutorial from some random place
in the internet instead of just looking
on what your doc says. So patterns for
getting simple versions of your docs
into the context of the LLM as it's
working with your product becomes
incredibly important. Um, and there's
still not a lot of real standards
outside of cursor rules, LLM.txt TXT and
and and and
MCP. Um, and again, when you're building
a platform, LLMs are not humans. Good DX
might not be good AX. One, one of my
favorite examples here is just like the
fact that LLMs works much better with
XML than with JSON.
And it's for the simple reason that that
that if you output XML, you don't have
to escape as many quotes and stuff as
when you output JSON. Um, but it's like
this this this weird unpredictable
change in like what's actually the best
format for for an LLM versus what have
history shown that developers
prefer. Another example of of good DX
not being BNX. This this was a really
interesting Twitter thread from Marcelo
Terrero at at BRICS that talked about um
how they actually kind of rearchitected
their front-end architecture to be more
LLM friendly. Um they removed all the
custom hooks within their codebase um
because those abstracted away what was
happening from the model. They started
making all data fetching use relay, a
GraphQL framework that sort of really
lets you define the data dependencies
directly in the in in the components.
And relay often has like really in the
market for developers have kind of not
really worn out because it was just like
too hard to to adopt. But it turns out
that that that if an agent understand
how it works and you put it in place, it
it can be really effective in letting
LLM's oneshot whole functionalities
because the context is simpler to reason
about. APIs are often not enough. APIs
are good, but if you just give an agent
an open API spec without anything else,
it'll probably perform worse at using
their product than if you give it
something like compute user operator
that that goes all the way through the
user interface. Um, so it's obvious that
that we need something else in between
and MCP is kind of emerging as as the
first good um standard for that. um
model context protocol you probably all
heard
about it's hard to say how many are sort
of deeply familiar with it now um but it
it really standardizes how applications
can give context to LLMs again the
question when an LLM uses your product
is often like this question of like how
do you actually get the right context in
front of it if you wanted to use your
API it becomes a qu question of like how
do you direct context? How can an API
call direct another API call after it's
done? How can you tie stateful flows
together and so on
and agent experience through all these
veins are are having remarkable effects
of companies ability to to to
differentiate, right? Like um one
question we often get in a world of of a
native tooling and VIP coding and so on
is like what's going to happen to the to
the developers. Um again as we built for
for agents and as we optimize Netlifi
for
agents my thesis is that we are
optimizing for the next 100 million
developers and for many more developers
that these tools will lower the barrier
to what it means to be a developer and
that we'll see lots more developers
enter the market that we'll see a lot of
developers work indirectly with code
instead of code but that what they're
doing is is still software development
and I can tell you that we are seeing
very similar charts on on on on our end
as as Paul is seeing from from Superbase
but it's fun to think about right like
that these tools that some people think
about as like taking over the role of
developer is actually like massively
driving exponential new levels of
signups for database company like
there's there's literally not much
tooling in the world out there that's
more developer centric than than a than
a database
company. We're seeing across the
ecosystem companies start adopting flows
that are similar to our deploy then
claim flow that really lowers the
barrier for an agent to initiate working
with your product before you have an
actual user using your product. This is
this is an example for for Neon Neon DB.
Um Prisma has has launched a similar
like deploy then claim flow. Um and I
think we'll see that becoming more and
more as a standard as often it becomes
an agent that makes the choice of the
initial tool set rather than a a human
doing that
directly. At Netlifi, we then also think
about customer AX in the terms of like
one thing is what are um what are we
building that makes Netleifi a better
platform for for agents to use and a
better platform to use with agents. Our
customers are obviously having a lot of
the same needs. And we just launched two
weeks ago the the ability for a to to
build MCP servers with Netlifi.
Um again, model context protocol is is
is still
early in in the terms of like it has
rough edges, but it's also very clearly
emerging as like one of the preferred
choices for getting agents access to
your to your project.
I I played around with it um vibe coded
and MCP server on on my personal blog.
You can check out the the the story
about it. Um but it's one of these
examples of how all of these things
plays together, right? Like so I was
actually able
to completely implement to completely
oneshot an MCP server for for my site
just by using the prompt. use the guide
here and a link to our guide on netlifi
to add a netifi function uh with an
example MCP server. Just giving that one
prompt to windf gave me a fully working
MCP server and then one follow-up prompt
to saying like implement these two
features these two tools immediately set
up an an an actual usable MCP server on
on on my own blog.
Then I added a third tool that's like a
a fun story in in terms of agent
experience in an agent net promoter
score
tool. And the the the my personal MCP it
really has two tools, right? Like so in
MCP you have a client, you set up cursor
or wind serve or claw chat and you tell
it like here here's an MCP server you
can you can use. The agent will then
discover what different tools there are
and try to use them when there's
relevant actions. And the first
functionalities I added was just like
list the articles on my blog and get a
specific article on my blog. But then I
added a third tool that's like leave
feedback in an agent net promoter score
survey and and tell as an agent how
happy are you with this MCP server um
and kind of notched agent into to to
doing this. So when they use one of the
other tools they are inclined to leave
feedback. and I currently have an agent
net promoter score of 50. Um, so so far
um both Claude and and and GPT4 pretty
happy with my MCP
server. The other feature we we we've
gotten a lot of requests from is is just
blocking AI bots and and controlling
crawlers.
AI tooling does tend aentic tooling does
tend to access the web in patterns that
are not always very desirable for people
that have websites, web stores or web
apps. And it's pretty clear that we we
need open standards and industry
calibration for ax for the web itself.
How should agents approach websites and
web apps? And that leads me to the third
point that we're working on in Netifi.
It's really the industry ax um open
standards for um how how agents can use
our products in ways that align with
with with how we want them to use them.
So if we see typical processes for for
human plus agent working with sites
today, we start seeing like tons of
scrapings and unneeded requests going
on. If we can optimize our projects for
um agents, we can get much more in
control of um the amount of of of
traffic agents drive and resources they
use. Um and um we can start really
thinking through how tool use can be
exposed not just through individual MCP
servers but but through the web. um how
we can think through better granular
access patterns than current OAF
standards allows for. Um how can we give
permissions to gated content to agents
in in ways where we can monetize and how
can we expose our own agents to for
other agents to interact with. If you're
interested in participating in this
discussion, we set up a a community site
agentexperience.exax AX where where
we're trying to drive discussions on on
how to build these shared standards and
and collaborate across the industry and
I invite you all to participate there or
uh read up on what Netifi is generally
doing in the in the Xa space. Thank you
so much.
Awesome. Thank you so much uh Matt. Very
very interesting. And uh maybe may maybe
we can take uh maybe we can take one
question. Yeah, absolutely. Yeah, we
have there's a ton of questions to be
honest, but I'm going to pick one. Um my
the the question I'd love to to to hear
is from from this side, from this point
of view, from the human aspect, what do
you feel like the biggest mental blocker
is for us as people to adopt to adapt to
using agent experience like you know in
in products today?
Um, I
think I think it's a lot about building
a new discipline, right? Like we spend a
lot of time like even now it's it's
often hard to be best-in-class at UX and
DX, right? Like because it's a hard
discipline. It requires you to to build
real empathy and to sit down and look at
real users of your product, right? Like
and in a similar way, we we now have
like this new
layer that that that interacts
with our products on behalf of a user,
right? Like so we start both having to
figure out like what what are the users
objectives and what kind of agents are
they trying to approach our product with
in the first place, right? like and
then putting ourself in in in those
shoes for as as developers for example.
Um, we often as experienced developers,
we've often built a lot of habits around
what it actually means to be a developer
and what it means to to to work with
code and and and to and to do software
development that might start really
shifting once we think about AI native
software development where where code is
often sort of a secondary artifact.
Um, I definitely experienced that in the
beginning as I first started trying some
of these tools, right? Like the whole
approach to fully understanding a system
in my head and then building a solution
to it versus the sort of more
probabilistic interactions with with an
agent where sometimes it almost feels
like you're you're arguing with someone
on on on how to do things, right?
Um, and as we're building products for
developers, remembering like that these
new patterns are are emerging and that
people are still navigating that space.
That's definitely like one one one of
the really interesting challenges that
sort of sits in in in the space between
like understanding
humans, understanding
LLMs and and and building the right kind
of product experience.
Awesome. Awesome. Matt, thank you so so
much. Great great session. And um yeah,
for those in fact I'll bring it back on
stage quickly. For those wanting to to
learn more uh about agent experience,
netifi.comex. Thanks Matt and thanks uh
for supporting the conference and giving
us a wonderful closing keynote. Thanks
for having